他们说，不平等从人类诞生的那天就存在，直到人类灭亡的那天也将存在，
they say in equity has been with us  since the beginning and will be with us
因为人们对这个问题根本不在乎。
until the end because people just don't  care.
我完全不同意这种观点。
I completely disagree
我相信，问题不是我们不在乎，而是我们不知道怎么做。
I believe we have more caring than we  know what to do with all of us here in
此刻在这个院子里的所有人，生命中总有这样或那样的时刻，目睹人类的悲剧，
this yard at one time or another have  seen human tragedies that broke our
感到万分伤心，但是我们什么也没做。
heart and yet we did nothing
并非我们无动于衷，而是因为我们不知道做什么和怎么做，如果我们知道
not because we didn't care but because we didn't know what to do if we had
如何做是有效的，那么我们就会采取行动，改变世界的障碍，
known how to help we would have acted . The barrier to change is not too little
并非由于人类的冷漠，而是世界实在太复杂，为把关心转变为行动，
carrying it is too much complexity to  turn carrying into action
我们需要找到问题，找到解决问题的方法和评估后果，但世界的复杂性使得
we need to see a problem see a solution  and see the impact. But complexity
所有这些步骤都难于做到。
blocks all three steps
即使有了互联网和24小时直播的新闻台，
even with the advent of the internet and  24-hour news
让人们真正发现问题所在仍然十分困难
it is still the complex enterprise to  get people to truly see the problems
当一架飞机坠毁了，官员们会立刻召开新闻发布会，
when an airplane crashes officials  immediately call a press conference
他们承诺进行调查，找到原因防止将来再次发生类似事故。
they promised to investigate determine  the cause and prevent similar crashes in
但是如果那些官员敢说真话，他们就会说，在今天这一天，
the future but if the officials were  brutally honest they would say of all
全世界所有可以避免的死亡之中，只有0.5%的死者来自于这次空难，
the people in the world who died today  from preventable causes one half of one percent.
我们决心尽一切努力调查
we're on this plane we're determined to  do everything possible to solve the
这个0.5%的死亡原因，显然，
problem that took the lives of the one  half of one percent the problem
更重要的问题不是这次空难，而是其他几百万可以预防的死亡事件，
is not just the plane crash but the millions of preventable dad's we don't
我们并没有很多机会了解那些死亡事件，媒体总是报告新闻，
read much about these death, the media  covers what's new and millions of people
而几百万人将要死去并非新闻，如果没有人报道，那么这些事件就很容易被忽视。
dying is nothing new so it stays in the  background where it's easy to ignore
另一方面，即使我们确实目睹了事件本身或看到了相关报道，
but even when we do see it or read about it
我们也很难持续关注这些事件。
it's difficult to keep our eye eyes on the problem
他人受苦是令人痛苦的，何况问题又如此复杂，我们根本不知道如何去帮助他人，
it's difficult to look at suffering if  the situation is so complex that we
所以我们会把脸转过去。
don't know how to help and so we look  away.
就算我们真正发现了问题所在，也不过是迈出了第一步，
if we can really see a problem which is  the first step
接着还有第二步
we come to the second step.
那就是从复杂的事件中找到解决办法，
cutting through the complexity to find a solution
如果我们要让关心落到实处，我们就必须找到解决办法。
finding solutions is essential if we want to make the most of our caring if
如果我们有一个清晰的和可靠的答案，
we have clear improvement answers
那么当任何组织或个人提出“我能如何提供帮助”时，
any time an organization or individual  asks how can I help
我们就能采取行动，我们就能够保证
then we can get action and we can make  sure that none of the caring in the
不浪费资源。
world is wasted
但是，世界的复杂性使得很难找到对全世界每一个有爱心的人都有效的行动方法，
the complexity makes it hard to mark a  path of action for everyone who cares
因此人类对他人的关心往往很难产生实际效果，
and makes it hard for their carrying to matter
从这个复杂的世界中找到解决方法，可以分为四个步骤，
cutting through complexity to find solutions runs through 4 predictable
确定目标，找到最高效的方法，
stages determine a goal find the highest  impact approach deliver the technology
发现适用于这个方法的新技术，
ideal for that approach
同时最聪明地利用现有的技术
and in the same time use the best  application of Technology you already have.
不管它是复杂的新药物，
whether it's something  so phisticated like the new drug or
还是最简单的蚊帐，艾滋病就是一个例子。
something simple like the bed net。 the  AIDS epidemic offers an example the
总的目标，毫无疑问是消灭这种疾病，最高效的方法是预防。
broad goal of course is to end the disease the highest leverage approach is   prevention.
最理想的技术是发明一种疫苗，
the ideal technology would be a vaccine
只要注射一次，就可以终生免疫。所以，政府、制药公司、基金会应该
that gives lifelong immunity with a single dose。 So governments drug
资助疫苗研究，但是，这样的研究工作
companies and foundations are funding vaccine research but their work is
很可能十年之内都无法完成，
likely to take more than a decade.
因此，与此同时，我们必须使用现有的技术，目前最有效的预防方法就是
so in the meantime we have to work with what we have in hand and the best
设法让人们避免那些危险的行为，要实现这个新的目标，
prevention approach we have now is  getting people to avoid risky behavior
又可以使用新的四步循环，这只是一种模式，
pursuing that goal starts the four-step  cycle again this is the pattern
关键的事情是永远不能停止思考和行动，我们千万不能
the crucial thing is to never stop  thinking and working and never do what
再犯上个世纪在疟疾和肺结核上犯过的错误，那时我们因为它们太复杂，
we did with malaria and tuberculosis in the 20th century which is to surrender
而放弃了采取行动，在发现问题和找到解决方法之后，
to complexity and quit.The final step  after seeing the problem and finding an
就是最后一步，评估工作结果，将你的成功或失败的经验传播出去，
approach is to measure the impact of the work and to share that success or
这样其他人就可以从你的努力中学得经验。当然，
failure so that others can learn from  the efforts. you have to have the
你必须有一些统计数字，你必须让他人知道。
statistics of course you have to be able  to show for example that a program is
你的项目为几百万儿童新接种了疫苗
vaccinating million more millions more  children
你也必须让他人知道儿童死亡率
you have to be able to show for example a decline in the number of children
下降了多少。
dying from the diseases
这些都是很关键的，不仅有利于改善项目效果，也有利于
this is essential not just to improve the program but also to help draw more
从商界和政府得到更多的帮助。 但是，如果你想鼓励其他人参加你的项目
investment from business and government.  But if you want to inspire people to participate
你就必须拿出更多的统计数字，必须展示你的项目的人性因素，
you have to show more than numbers. You  have to convey the human impact of the
这样其他人就会感到拯救一个生命，对那些处在困境中的家庭到底意味着什么。
work so people can feel what saving a  life means to the families affected
记得几年前我去参加世界经济论坛，旁听一个全球健康问题会议，
I remember going to the World Economic  Forum some years back and sitting on a
会议的内容有关于如何拯救几百万条生命，是几百万
global help panel that was discussing  ways to save millions of lives millions
想一想吧，拯救一个人的生命已经让人何等激动，现在你要把这种激动
think of the thrill if you could save  just one person's life then multiply
再乘上几百万倍。
that by millions yet
但不幸的是，这是我参加过的最最乏味的论坛，
this was the most boring panel I've ever  been on ever so boring
乏味到令我几欲先走。
even I couldn't stand.
那次经历之所以让我难忘，是因为之前
what made that experience especially  striking was that I just come from an
我们刚刚发布了一个软件的第13版本，我们让观众激动得跳了起来，
event where we were introducing version 13 of some piece of software and we had
欢呼雀跃。
people jumping and shouting with  excitement.
我喜欢人们因为软件而感到激动，那么我们为什么不能让人们因为
I love getting people excited about  software but why can't we generate even
能够拯救生命而感到更加激动呢？
more excitement for saving lives?
除非你能够让人们看到或感受到
you can't get people excited
行动的影响力，否则你无法让人们激动。
unless you can help them see and feel  the impact
如何做到这一点并不是一件简单的事
the way to do that is another complex  question
同前面一样，在这个问题上我依然是乐观的。
still I'm optimistic
不错，人类的不平等有史以来一直存在，但那些能够化繁为简的
yes in equity has been with us forever  but the new tools we have to cut through
新工具却是最近才出现的。
complexity have not been with us forever
这些新工具可以帮助我们将人类的同情心发挥到极致。
they are new they can help us make the  most of our caring and that's why the
这就是为什么未来和过去是不一样的，这个时代无时无刻不在涌现新的变革
future can be different from the past . The defining and ongoing innovations  of this age,
生物技术，个人计算机，互联网，
biotechnology the personal computer and  the Internet
它们给了我们一个从未有过的机会去终结那些极端的贫穷
give us a chance we've never had before  to end extreme poverty and n debt from
和非恶性疾病的死亡，60年前，乔治.马歇尔也是在这个地方的毕业典礼上
preventable disease 60 years ago George  Marshall came to this commencement and
宣布了一个计划，帮助战后的欧洲国家的建设，
he announced a plan to assist the  nation's a post-war Europe
他说：“我认为，困难的一点是这个问题太复杂，报纸和电台向公众
he said quote I think one difficulty is  that the problem is one of such enormous
源源不断地提供各种事实，
complexity that the very massive facts  presented to the public by press and
使得大街上的普通人要清晰地判断形势
radio make it exceedingly difficult for  the man in the street to reach a clear
变得非常困难。事实上，经过层层传播，
appraisement of the situation. it is  virtually impossible at this distance to
想要真正地把握形势，
grasp at all.
是根本不可能的。”
the real significance of the situation
马歇尔发表这个演讲之后的三十年，我那一届学生毕业，
30 years after Marshall made his address  which was 30 years ago as my class
当然我不在其中。
graduated without me.
那时，新技术刚刚开始萌芽，它们将使得这个世界变得更小、更开放、
technology was emerging that would make the world smaller more open more visible
更容易看到、距离更近。
less distance. The emergence